Robert H. Taylor Collection of English and American Literature, 1280s-1958 (bulk 1800s-1930s ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Series 1: Modern (Bound) Manuscripts, 1600-1958; 7 shelves
  - KIPLING, RUDYARD (1865-1936). "Tomlinson.", circa 1890; 1 volume, 7 leaves
    Typescript of Kipling's poem with manuscript corrections in pen, written in an unidentified hand. Together with a ALS, written in pencil from W. E. H. [William Ernest Henley] to Mrs. Dunn concerning this poem, dated Sunday 11 Howard Place, Edinburgh.
  - LAMB, CHARLES (1775-1834). "My First Play.", circa 1821; 1 volume, 3 pp.
    Autograph manuscript of an essay with Lamb's revisions and deletions. Sent through the post to Messrs. Taylor and Hessey for publication in The London Magazine, 1821 The verso of the second leaf has the address and postmark, and the remains of the seal.
  - LAMB, CHARLES (1775-1834). "On an Infant Dying as soon as Born.", 1827; 1 volume, 4 pp.
    Autograph manuscript of a poem sent through the post to T. Hood and postmarked 1827 Bound together with two engraved portraits, one of the author and the other of Thomas Hood.
  - LAMB, CHARLES (1775-1834). "Sweet is Thy Sunny Hair.", 1800s; 1 leaf, 2 pp.
    Autograph manuscript poem (3 stanzas, 33 lines), signed with initials. Title from first line.
  - LAMB, CHARLES (1775-1834). "Theatralia, etc.", 1800s; 1 volume, 131, 36 pp.
    Notebook containing extracts from the works of Charles Lamb, written in pen in the hand of Mary Shelley. Titles include Theatralia, On the Genius & Character of Hogarth, etc. Together with notes and passages from Greek tragedy translated into English, written in pen in the hand of Thomas Love Peacock.
  - LANDOR, WALTER SAVAGE (1775-1864). "Commonplace Book.", 1800s; 1 volume, 33 leaves
    Commonplace book with revisions and deletions. Contains Landor's thoughts and opinions on various aspects of life and literature. There are comments on old age, on Napoleon, and on a host of writers and poets including Shakespeare, Milton, Tennyson, Pope, Byron, Wordsworth, Gibbon, Sterne, Coleridge, Otway, and Voltaire. There are also passages on Elizabethan poets, and on the progress of poetry in general, with a tribute to Sir Walter Scott.
  - LANDOR, WALTER SAVAGE (1775-1864). "Original Poems and Letters.", 1800s; 1 volume, 8 leaves
    Includes an AMS of his poem "To the Worm" (3 pp.) dated Apr. 22 [no year] and followed by a typed transcription. Also includes ALS from Landor to Lady Blessington, undated (2 pp.) and AMS, signed with initials, of a poem with the first line "A Most Puissant Picture-Scouring Prince."
  - LEAR, EDWARD (1812-88). "Alphabet.", 1871; 1 volume, 14 leaves
    Signed autograph manuscript of an alphabet written and illustrated by Lear for a little boy, Walter G. Clay. Written on 26 oblong slips and mounted in an album preceded by a signed autograph poem presenting the alphabet.
  - LOGAN, STANLEY (1885-1953). "Zuleika Dobson: a Play with Music in Two Acts.", 1900s; 1 volume, 98 leaves
    Typescript copy.
  - LUTTRELL, NARCISSUS (1657-1732). "Rent and Tenant Records, Middlesex County and Vicinity.", 1 volume, 108 leaves
    Notebook kept by Luttrell and others pertaining to the Luttrell estates. Contains rent and tenant records in Middlesex County and vicinity. And includes transcriptions of manorial rent records circa 1550-1650 for the manors of Rialton, Hadley, Polsue, and Golowras. Also contains methods of land surveys in Cornwall, etc., and definitions of legal terms pertaining to land tenure. There is a brief history of early printing (1 leaf, 14 x 7 cm.) laid in.
  - Marvell, Andrew, "The Second advice to a painter for drawing the history of our navall bussinesse in imitation of Mr. Waller being the last work of Sir John Denham [...]", 1666; 225; AM 2016-50; Marvell, Andrew, 1621-1678; 1 volume 20 folios (1 blank) 22.3 x 17.6 cm in contemporary marbled-paper wrapper
    This scribal copy is of key satires of the 1660s, now usually attributed to poet Andrew Marvell. The Second and Third Advice poems, written in imitation of Edmund Waller's "Instructions to a Painter" (1664), take as their subject the conduct of the Second Anglo-Dutch War, especially that of the Royal Navy with the Duke of York as Lord High Admiral. Both poems circulated initially in manuscript: some fifty manuscript copies of the Second Advice are known, and thirty-three copies of the Third. Many manuscript copies attributed the poems to Sir John Denham, which hid their true author behind a wry joke.
    Also included are two texts, "On Doctor Poore[...]" and "On Doctor Lee."
    Purchased at Pirie auction at Sotheby’s, 2015
    Stanley family, Earls of Derby, of Knowsley, Merseyside (note and shelf-mark on wrapper). Previous acquisition: Seven Gables, 1960
  - MASEFIELD, JOHN (1878-1967). "William Shakespeare: A Study, with Scenes from the Plays.", 1958; 1 volume, about 45 leaves
    Consists of a typescript, with pencil annotations, of an adaptation of Masefield's early book on Shakespeare that was first published in 1911 and revised in 1954. This version was clearly designed for the stage and was made (or possibly only for) Alec Clunes, one of the leading English actors of the post-war years. The title page states that it is his property (c/o the Arts Theatre Club in London). Loosely inserted are several copies of a program for performances at the Hague and Amsterdam ("Alec Clunes presents William Shakespeare from a Study by John Masefield"). The typed leaves have been pasted into a bound volume (half morocco) on country homes, with spine labeled "Country Homes". A number of printed drawings of country homes remain in the volume.
  - MAYHEW, JAMES (1771-1845). "Book of Memorandums.", 1793; 1 volume, 35 leaves
    Autograph manuscript with detailed pen-and-ink diagrams of the renovation projects for the Drury Lane Theatre. The theatre was managed by R. B. Sheridan and closed for renovations from 1791-1794
  - MAYHEW, JAMES (1771-1845). "Masonry Notebook.", 1784; 1 volume, 42 pp., 8 leaves
    Contains notes on calculations for joiners, bricklayers, plasterers' work, etc. Possibly used during the renovation of the Drury Lane Theatre. Bound together with a printed text Tables of Arithmetic.
  - MILLAIS, JOHN EVERETT (1829-1896). "Orley Farm.", circa 1860; 1 volume, 40 leaves
    India paper proofs of the drawings for Orley Farm by J. E. Millais, engraved on wood by George Dalziel and the Dalziel Brothers.
  - MORRIS, WILLIAM (1834-1896). "The Story of King Magnus the Barefoot.", 1800s; 1 volume, 30 leaves
    Autograph manuscript of a translation by E. Magnusson and Morris of a Norse story, written in the hand of Magnusson with many corrections and alterations in the hand of Morris. Together with 20 autograph manuscript poems by Morris.
  - NORTH, DUDLEY (1581-1666). "A Forest of Varieties.", circa 1640; 1 volume, 84 pp.
    Manuscript, written in an unidentified contemporary hand, with autograph corrections by the author. Also includes a letter from Edward Scott, British Museum, 1896 June 2 concerning the manuscript.
  - ORRERY, ROGER BOYLE, EARL OF (1621-1679). "The Black Prince.", circa 1669; 1 volume, 126 pp.
    Manuscript copy, written in an unidentified contemporary hand, with the author's autograph corrections.
  - ORRERY, ROGER BOYLE, EARL OF (1621-1679). "History of Henry the Fifth.", 1600s; 1 volume, 79 pp.
    Manuscript copy, without title or indication of authorship. It preserves the two lines spoken by Tudor in the beginning of Act III, which do not occur, in the early printed versions. Contains at least one stage direction. Later printed in 1668 (London: H. Herringman).
  - PAGE, ANTHONY (compiler). "Commonplace book on English law.", 1640-1660; Page, Anthony; 1 volume 22x14 cm
    The compiler, Anthony Page, interleaved pages from published law books relating to Roman law (e.g. Justinian's INSTITUTES and a summary of Justinian's DIGESTS) and English Common Law (e.g. Register of Writs, GOLDBOLT'S REPORTS) with handwritten transcriptions from contemporary printed books (chiefly on law and government), and notes on literature, epitaphs, weights and measures, and other subjects. The contents is in Latin, English, and Anglo-Norman (i.e., Law French).
    Admitted to Lincoln's Inn on 20 February 1609, Anthony Page was an English counselor of law in his native Saxthorpe, Norfolk, during the 1620s and 1630s. He died in 1661.
  - PEART, JOSHUA. "Poems and Songs upon Several Occasions.", 1726; 1 volume, 191 leaves
    Commonplace book of English poetry, compiled by Joshua Peart. Contains transcriptions of 17th-century poetry, satyrs, fables, etc.
  - PEMBROKE, WILLIAM HERBERT, 3RD EARL OF (1580-1630). "Autograph Letter Signed to Viscount Lisle.", 1626 June 16; 1 leaf, 4 pp.
    Concerns a dinner party with Lord Carlisle.
  - "The Pleasures of Single Life, or, The Miseries of Matrimony.", 1600s; 1 volume, 15 pp.
    Manuscript poem, written in an unidentified hand.
  - POTENGER, JOHN, "A Collection of Miscellanies in Prose & Verse", circa 1725; AM 2016-87; 1 volume 106 leaves 20 x 16 cm in contemporary marbled boards, waxed paper spine
    A collection of poetry and prose by the published English poet, including substantial amounts of verse that is apparently unrecorded. Written in brown ink almost all in a single, sloping hand, possibly that of the author.
    Microfilm copy #1743
  - READE, CHARLES (1814-1884). "Charles Reade's Letter Book.", dates not examined; 89; 3 volumes, volume 1, 91 leaves
    Scrapbook of letters (91 leaves, c. 250 items) primarily from Reade's friends and acquaintances in literary and drama circles, heavily annotated by Reade. Together with typed transcripts (2 volumes) of the album's contents. Includes correspondence with Dion Boucicault (Agnes Robertson), Miss Braddon, John Blackwood, Wilkie Collins, Ada Cavendish, Charles Dickens, Edward Dicey, Sutherland Edwards, John Forster, Victor Hugo, Henry James, James Lambert, Mark Lemon, Bulwer Lytton, W.C. Macready, Millais, George Augustus Sala, Robert Southey, Mrs. Laura Seymour, Kate Terry, Ellen Terry, Anthony Trollope, Martin Tupper, Mark Twain (Samuel L. Clemens), Emile Zola (written in French), the Law Office of Chase & Nelson, etc. Also contains several documents and manuscripts including: AMs draft (2 p.) of Richmond's speech from King's Rival, inserted by Reade in co-author Taylor's act, undated; ADS (1 p.) a contract by Reade and Mark Lemon (as representative for Herbert Ingram) for Reade's White Lies, dated 1857 DS (2 p.) a contract with Tauchnitz (1 p., fol. 70v) written in German relating to Peg Woffington, a Terrible Temptation, and Christie Johnstone, dated 1872 ADS (1 p.) an agreement with Henry Pettitt regarding Reade's Love and Money, dated 1882 DS (1 p., fol. 73v) a nomination of Reade as a Steward of the anniversary dinner of the Royal Literary Fund, undated; DS (1 p., fol. 75v) a money order, dated 1871 Document (1 p., fol. 71r) an analysis in tabular form of the account of Reade and Bentley delivered previous to the injunction for Peg Woffington, and Christie Johnstone, undated (printed on satin); DS (1 p., fol.36r) a dinner invitation in the form of a passport, dated 1855 DS (1 p.) a photograph of Reade, dated 1866 Galley proof (1 p., fol. 47r) of "A Suppressed Letter," published in the Pall Mall Gazette, circa 1845-1984
  - REPTON, HUMPHRY (1752-1818). "Beau-Desert in Staffordshire.", 1814; 1 volume, 21 leaves
    Contains before-and-after watercolor views of his suggested improvements to the estate of Beaudesert in Staffordshire prepared for Lord Uxbridge (Henry William Paget, 2nd Earl of Uxbridge, 1768-1854). Contains 14 drawings and 12 leaves of text. For more information see: David R. Coffin, "Repton’s 'Red Book' for Beaudesert," in Coffin, Magnificent Buildings, Splendid Gardens (Princeton: Department of Art and Archeology, Princeton University Press, 2008), pp. 200-217.
  - RESTORATION VERSE MISCELLANY, circa 1670s; AM 2015-58; 1 volume
    Of French origin, this volume contains 17 poems and epigrams, in English, Latin, and French likely kept during the 1670s. Contents include the following: (1) Katherine Philips (1632-1664), "On the numerous access of the English to waite upon his Ma[jes]ti in Flanders' ("Hasten greate Prince unto the Brittish Isles..."); (2) Andrew Marvell (1621-1678), Epigram on Thomas Blood's attempted theft of the Crown Jewels in Latin ("Bloodius, ut fundi damnum repararet aviti...") and English "Whilest valiant Blood, his Rents to have regaine'd..."); (3) "An Epitaph on Moliere," in French (with an English translation ("Here lyes the fam'd Moliere, who was at strife..."); (4) Other poems and epigrams. Paper, 25.3 x 20.4 cm; 34 folios; text is written by at least 3 hands on fols. 3r-8v, and the remaining folios are blank; bound in limp-parchment wrapper.
    Written in English, French, and Latin.
  - ROSSETTI, DANTE GABRIEL (1828-1882). "The Bride's Prelude.", circa 1880; 1 leaf, 2 pp.
    Autograph manuscript of the first draft, with annotations by William Michael Rossetti (2 leaves, 4 pp.). Together with the advertisement for Dante and His Circle (1 leaf, 1 p.) and notes on the proportions of the head in relation to various parts of the body.
  - SCOTT, WALTER (1771-1832). "Autograph Letter Signed with Initials to John Ballantyne.", 1811 May 6; 1 leaf, 4 pp.
    Concerns the scheme for the vision of Don Roderick and gives his first version of the first five stanzas for which Scott begs "James's opinion and that speedily..."
  - SCOTT, WALTER (1771-1832). "Contract with Sir Walter Scott for Copyright of Ivanhoe, The Monastery, The Abbot, and Kenilworth.", 1821 November 3; 1 volume, 2 leaves
    Signed document. Also concerns publication of these works by Archibald Constable and Company.
  - SCOTT, WALTER (1771-1832). "The Field of Waterloo.", circa 1815; 1 volume, 27 leaves
    Signed autograph manuscript of the poem, with notes.
  - SCOTT, WALTER (1771-1832). "The Vision of Don Roderick.", 1811; 1 volume, 27 leaves
    Autograph manuscript with corrections and additions. Consists of a preface, dated 1811 June 14 (complete); Introduction of 12 stanzas (complete); text, stanzas I-XVII and LV-LXIII; conclusion (complete); and notes from the poem, written in an unidentified hand.
  - SHAW, BERNARD (1856-1950). "Cashel Byron's Profession.", 1886; 1 volume, 164 pp.
    Shaw's copy of the 1st edition of this work, with annotations and revisions in Shaw's hand for the "New Edition, Revised," published in 1889. This copy was used by the printers of the 1889 edition and contains penciled markings made in the printing house.
  - SHAW, BERNARD (1856-1950). "The Dramatic Censorship.", 1912; 1 volume, 8 leaves
    Signed autograph manuscript concerning the suppression of Israel Zangwill's play The Next Religion. Together with a proof copy with autograph corrections.
  - SHAW, BERNARD (1856-1950). "Preface for Politicians.", 1907; 1 volume, 93 leaves
    Typescript of the "Preface for Politicians" from John Bull's Other Island. Together with a signed autograph manuscript of the "Conclusion for the Preface for Politicians."
  - (SHAW, BERNARD 1856-1950). "Shakes versus Shav.", circa 1949; 1 volume, 12 leaves
    Autograph manuscript in Gregg shorthand, with an autograph note. Together with 2 photographs of Shaw and a corrected typescript.
  - SHAW, BERNARD (1856-1950). "An Unsocial Socialist.", circa 1886; 1 volume, 250 pp.
    The printer's (setting) copy, extensively revised throughout in Shaw's hand. This is Shaw's copy of the original magazine publication of his second novel, extensively revised and augmented by Shaw for the first book edition, published in 1887 by Swan, Sonnenschein, Lowry, & Co. The revisions and additions include the autograph manuscript insertion of 2 pages pasted together to make one page at p. 113 and 6 pages of autograph manuscript inserted at p. 219. Lacks 10 leaves between p. 144 and 155.
  - SHELLEY, PERCY BYSSHE (1792-1822), 1811 October 21; 1 item, 6 leaves
    Autograph Letter Signed to T.C. Medwin. Concerns marriage settlements with Harriet Westbrook.
  - SHELLEY, PERCY BYSSHE (1792-1822). "Edipus Tyrannus, or, Swellfoot the Tyrant.", 1820; 1 volume, 25 leaves
    Manuscript copy by John Gisborne from "Shelley's manuscript No. 5."
  - SHERIDAN, ELIZABETH ANN (1754-1792). "Commonplace Book.", 1782; 1 volume, 280 pp.
    Contains transcripts of verses by her husband (R. B. Sheridan) herself, her relatives, and friends. Written entirely in the hand of E. A. Sheridan. Most pieces signed with initials of the authors.
  - SHERIDAN, JANE GEORGIANA (1809-1884). "Commonplace Book.", 1825; 1 volume, 40 leaves
    Contains manuscript verse, epitaphs, etc. Also includes watercolor, pen-and-ink, and pencil drawings of people, fairies, animals, flowers, etc.
  - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816), 1770-1806; 17 volumes
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "Autograph Manuscript Poems, Commonplace Book, etc.", 1770-1814; 1 volume, approx. 80 leaves in various foliations
      Consists of autograph manuscript verse, 14 drafts of verses, scenarios, and fragments of manuscripts; manuscript verses (27 leaves) in handwriting of Sheridan and copies of others written by him, including "Triumph of the Whale"; manuscript copies of imperial patents (2) dated 1804 and 1805 copied from the Imperial Patent Office, probably intended for theatrical pieces; a notebook (39 leaves) of a collection of verses in contemporary hand, written by members of Sheridan's circle, including "The Grotto"; a manuscript, written in an unidentified hand, of a drama "Rural Amours, a musical drama," by Elizabeth Ann Linley Sheridan, dated circa 1785 a manuscript fragment titled "On Mrs. B.," by Ch. Fox [Charles James Fox], undated; and ALS to Thomas Moore from J.H. concerning his research on the life of Sheridan, undated
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The Duenna", 1777 April 15; 1 volume, 146 leaves Bound in contemporary red morocco, with gilt borders, spine, and edges, and marbled endpapers. Bears contemporary bookplate of "Martha Saunders 1777."
      Early scribal manuscript of Sheridan's THE DUENNA. Pre-dates the authorized published edition of 1794.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The Forty Thieves.", circa 1806; 1 volume, 72 leaves
      Manuscript of a drama, written in an unidentified hand, said to be written by Thomas Sheridan. The work is commonly attributed to R. B. Sheridan.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "Indenture.", 1794; 1 volume, 7, 75 pp.
      Contemporary manuscript copy of an indenture, by which Sheridan and Thomas Linley vested control of the Theatre Royal in Drury Lane in the hands of three trustees, Albany Wallis, Richard Ford, and Thomas Hammersley.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The School for Scandal.", 1777; 1 volume, 216, 8 leaves
      Contemporary manuscript promptbook with autograph corrections by Sheridan.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The School for Scandal.", circa 1777; 1 volume, 21 leaves
      Contemporary manuscript copy of Sir Peter Teazle's part, with some corrections in text, written in several different hands.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The School for Scandal.", circa 1777; 2 volume, 46 leaves
      Autograph manuscript of an early draft of the play, which later developed into The School for Scandal. The first notebook contains the play to the end of the discovery scene and a paragraph of suggested dialogue for the 5th act. The second notebook begins with Act IV, scene I. This version of the scene introduced "Sir Oliver" disguised as a poor relation, differing in respect from the version of the first notebook.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The School for Scandal.", circa 1777; 1 volume, 84 pp.
      Scribal copy with theatrical markings added in a second hand.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The School for Scandal.", circa 1777; 1 volume, 209 leaves
      Scribal copy, with some corrections in a second hand.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The School for Scandal.", circa 1780; 1 volume, 91 leaves
      Scribal manuscript with Monogram "MW" on cover. Text very similar to the Dublin unauthorized 1780 printed edition.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The School for Scandal.", circa 1780; 1 volume, 64 pp.
      Scribal manuscript.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The School for Scandal.", circa 1780-1784; AM 2018-101; 1 volume 22.8 x 18 cm Late 18th century red straight-grained morocco, the covers with wide gilt roll-tooled borders, spine gilt, gilt edges, marbled endpapers bound in the style of Richard Wier
      Consists of a very early bound contemporary scribal manuscript, written by an unknown hand. The manuscript predates any authorized publications of the play, and the list of actors it contains reflects that of the earliest performances. While there is no title page, the manuscript also includes the prefatory poem "A Portrait," a poetical address to Frances Anne Crewe (1748-1818), which is subtitled "Address'd to Mrs Crewe with the Comedy of the School for Scandal by R.B. Sheridan Esqr," as well as the full text of both David Garrick's prologue and George Colman's epilogue.
      Purchase, 2018.
      Contains a contemporary armorial bookplate of Martha Saunders, dated 1777.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The School for Scandal." Contemporary manuscript promptbook, circa 1797; 1 volume, 93 leaves
      Contains the cast of the original production and the authentic text, which was not published until 1799
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The School for Scandal.", circa 1813; 1 volume, 142 pp.
      Manuscript prompt copy with prompter's name [Hallot] and date 1813 on p. 48. Copy contains detailed descriptions of the settings put forth at the beginning of each act.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The School for Scandal.", circa 1777; 1 volume, 238 leaves
      Autograph manuscript sketch (18 leaves) interleaved with the printed text from the edition of Sheridan's works by his biographer, Thomas Moore 1821 Together with another autograph manuscript sketch (108 leaves) interleaved with the text from an edition of Sheridan's works by Thomas Moore.
    - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY (1751-1816). "The Statesman.", circa 1781; 1 volume, 22 pp.
      Autograph manuscript of Act I, written by John Dent and revised by Sheridan (authorship has been attributed to both). Contains annotations, additions, and revisions in Sheridan's hand.
  - "Song Book.", 1700s; 1 volume, 127 leaves
    Manuscript song book, written in an unidentified 18th century hand, Incomplete, begins with number 742 and ends with number 1735
  - SOUTHEY, ROBERT (1774-1843). "Commonplace Book.", circa 1828; 1 volume, 102 leaves
    Contains notes on Southey's extensive literary and historical readings. Topics include the Navy from the time of King Henry II to Rodney. There are numerous transcripts of letters written by admirals of the fleet during the Dutch war and later, some extracts from Charnock, and notes on pirates and their exploits. Many notes relate to Naval affairs of the 17th century. There are also literary notes on Sir Philip Sidney, Thomas Kyd, Ben Johnson, and Shakespeare. Dated from endpapers watermark date.
  - STEVENS, JOHN (d. 1726). Miscellany, 1679-1690; 1 volume, approx. 500 pp.